Guide to the Conversational Club Collection, 1862 - [ongoing]
Conversational Club Collection, 1862 - [ongoing]
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Conversational Club (Middletown, Conn.)
1000-30
4.5
10
The Conversational Club was formed in 1862 by the faculty of Wesleyan University to discuss topics of interest along with other Middletown residents.
The collection has four series: Minutes, Chronological Files, Addition of June 2008, and Addition of December 2009.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Given by club members prior to 1997 (Acc. 1000-20), Kay Briggs in 2000 (Acc. 2000-45), Karl Scheibe in 2008 (Acc. 2008-10), and John Shaw in 2009 (Acc. 2009-50).
Historical Note
The Conversational Club was formed in 1862 by the faculty of Wesleyan University to discuss topics of interest along with other Middletown residents. Meetings typically included dinner, a paper delivered by a club member, followed by discussion. Meetings rotated among the homes of the club members. Topics included world events, scientific and literary topics, philosophy, and anything else of general interest. The membership of the club was all male until 1987.
Collection Overview
The collection has four series: Minutes, Chronological Files, Addition of June 2008, and Addition of December 2009. The Chronlogical Files include meeting notes, speeches, reply cards, bills, invitations, attendance lists, and other materials documenting club meetings. The Addition of June 2008 (Acc. 2008-10) includes program announcements, including members names and topics of discussion, from 1870 to 1963. It also includes some papers read at meetings, correspondence, meeting programs, financial information, and photographs. The materials have been arranged in roughly chronological order. The Addition of December 2009 (Acc. 2009-50) includes minutes and abstracts of meetings from January 2003 to May 2006.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Conversational Club (Middletown, Conn.); Middletown (Conn.) --History.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Minutes, 1862-1970
  - Notes from Secretary's Record, November 17, 1862-January 24, 1876 (Box 1)
  - Book I: Minutes, 1862
  - Book II: Minutes, 1879-1893
  - Book III: Minutes, 1893-1908
  - Book IV: Minutes, 1908-1921
  - Book V: Minutes, 1921-1934 (Box 2)
  - Book VI: Minutes, 1934-1947
  - Book VII: Minutes, January 20, 1947- December 4, 1950 (Box 3)
  - Book VIII: Minutes, January 15, 1951- February 2, 1953
  - Minutes, 1953-1958 (Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1958-1961 (Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1961-1963 (Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1954-1970 (Folder 4)
- Chronological Files, 1887-1999
  - 1887-1900 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Undated handwritten club histories
    - Club Notes: a paper read at the regular meeting of the Conversational Club, by O. Vincent Coffin, November 21, 1887
    - Invitation, November 16, 1887
    - Treasurer's report, 1899
    - Invitation, February 1900
    - Bills and receipts, 1898-1900
    - Attendence, 1893-1900
  - 1900-1910 (Folder 2-7)
    - Memorial minutes, circa 1900-1910
    - Fortieth Anniversary Invitation, 1902
    - Bills, 1903-1910
    - Letters received, 1904-1910
    - Reports, 1904, 1910
    - A few days in the fjords of Norway, George A. Craig, April 27, 1908
  - 1911-1919 (Folder 8-13)
    - Co-operative Building and Loan Association, Shanklin, December 18, 1911
    - Submarine War-Craft, April 19, 1915
    - Correspondence, 1916
    - Memorial minutes, 1917
    - Prohibition, 1918
    - Something about the Federal Reserve Bank, George A. Craig, February 17, 1919
  - 1921-1928 (Folder 14-23)
    - Commonplaces, Prof. Andrew C. Armstrong, circa 1920
    - Something about foreign exchange, G. A. Craig, November 14, 1921
    - Record of meetings, 1921-1926
    - Invitation, Sixtieth Anniversary, November 6, 1922
    - Things learned and unlearned since 1914, A.C. Armstrong, November 3, 1924
    - The industrial and agricultural future of Connecticut, E. Kent Hubbard, November 17, 1924
    - The stuff of which our life is made, R. [Fauley?], January 5, 1925
    - A Connecticut Crook, George A. Craig, April 6, 1925
    - Early banking and banks in Connecticut, George A. Craig, January 3, 1927
    - A home institution (Long Lane Farm), George A. Craig, November 5, 1928
  - Method, A.C. Armstrong, November 7, 1932 (Folder 24)
  - 1937 (Folder 25-28)
    - Correspondence, 1937
    - Invitation, seventy-fifth anniversary, 1937
    - Remarks of the Honorable E. Kent Hubbard, January 4, 1937
    - Club history, on 75th anniversary, Karl D. Harrington, November 15, 1937
  - 1940-1949 (Folder 29-34)
    - Great Britain and India, Morris B. Crawford, April 15, 1940
    - Records of meetings, 1940-1949
    - The need for defense against military and economic aggression, E. Kent Hubbard, February 3, 1941
    - The parable of the irrational points, B. H. Camp, April 21, 1941
    - Supplementary historical notes, May 20, 1946
    - Group photo, 1949
  - 1962 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - A Commemorative Pamphlet, 1862-1962 (2 copies)
    - The Conversational Club, 1862-1962: The First Century
  - 1964-1969 (Folder 2-7)
    - Records of meetings, 1964-1969
    - Speeches
      - Made, not born: the life and times of J.S. Carberry, John W. Spaeth, March 16, 1964
      - What do you want?, T.C. Dunham, April 19, 1965
      - 28 Wooster Street, Burton H. Camp, February 7, 1966
      - Thee and me, Jules D. Holzberg, January 9, 1967
      - The communication of the gospel in a secular age, Rev. Joseph C. Harvey, April 3, 1967
      - 1897, Burton H. Camp, April 8, 1968
    - Schedules of meetings, 1966-1967
    - Schedules of meetings, 1967-1968
    - Schedules of meetings, 1968-1969
    - Schedules of meetings, 1969-1970
  - October 1970-1971
    - Minutes (Folder 8)
    - The Ivory Tower by Burton H. Camp, October 19, 1970
    - Hero?--Anti-Hero, November 2, 1970
    - The Greening of America, summary of paper delivered by Edwin D. Etherington, December 7, 1970
    - Who Minds the Store, newspaper article by John Kenneth Galbraith, December 7, 1970
    - Abstract of a talk, The Private Press, by Wyman W. Parker, January 11, 1971
    - Summary of paper, West of Philadelphia, by Donald G. Arnault, February 1, 1971
    - The Delicate Air, April 5, 1971
    - The Last of the Big-Time Spenders, by Ralph H. Shaw the 2nd, October 4, 1971
    - Record of meetings, 1970
    - Correspondence, 1970
    - Constitution, 1970
    - Summary of meeting and speech, October 6, 1970
    - Schedules of meetings, 1970-1971 (Folder 9)
  - 1971
    - Records of meetings, 1971 (Folder 10)
    - Summaries of meetings and speeches, November-December 1971
    - Correspondence, 1971
    - Q.H.F. and Others, John W. Spaeth, Jr., March 1, 1971
    - Memorial minute, October 4, 1971
    - Music program, November 1, 1971
    - The stuff of fiction, John W. Paton, December 6, 1971
    - Schedules of meetings, 1971-1972 (Folder 11)
  - 1972
    - Records of meetings, 1972 (Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1972
    - Served dinner suggestions, April 10, 1972
    - Summaries of meetings and speeches, February-December 1972
    - Schedules of meetings, 1972-1973 (Folder 13)
  - 1973
    - Summaries of meetings and speeches, January-December 1973 (Folder 14)
    - Not for bread alone, Victor L. Butterfield, January 8, 1973 (Folder 15)
    - Records of meetings, 1973
    - Correspondence, 1973
    - Schedules of meetings, 1973-1974 (Folder 16)
  - 1974
    - Summaries of meetings and speeches, January-December 1974 (Folder 17)
    - F.R. and C.R., Gordon B. McWilliams, March 4, 1974 (Folder 18)
    - A chicken in the pot, Max Tishler, December 2, 1974
    - Schedules of meetings, 1974-1975 (Folder 19)
  - 1975-1976
    - Summaries of meetings and speeches, January-May 1976 (Folder 20)
      - Minutes
      - American Bird Photographers and Bird Photography by Joseph R. Swain, May 5, 1975
      - The Drafting of the Declaration of Independence
      - Precis--The Man Who Couldn't Seak Japanese
      - Summary of paper on Near Eastern themes: Tawfik al-HJakim, Egyptian Abrabic literature by Mehadin K. Arafeh
      - The P of P & Z (planning and zoning) by R. H. Shaw, II, February 2, 1976
      - Grandfather and Leo, summary of paper delivered April 5, 1976
      - Influences, a precis speech about education, by John W. Paton
    - Schedules of metings, 1975-1976 (Folder 21)
  - 1976-1977 (Folder 22)
    - Election letter, October 1976
    - Summaries of meetings and speeches, 1976-1977
      - Minutes
      - f/64 paper on Ansel Adams by Russell G. D'Oench, Jr.
      - Myths and Paradigms: The Interaction of Humanities and Scientists summary of a presentation to the club, February 7, 1977
    - Schedules of metings, 1976-1977
  - 1977-1978
    - Summaries of meetings and speeches, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Minutes
      - Summary of Mr. Lockwood's paper, October 3, 1977
      - 'Tis the Seanson Melancholy by Mr. Roberts
      - Summary, For Better or For Worse
      - Abstract, Skulduggery in Middletown
    - Schedules of metings, 1977-1978 (Folder 2)
  - 1978-1979
    - Summaries of meetings and speeches, 1978-1979 (Folder 3)
      - Minutes
      - M I I: Help! by J.R. Swain (Indian ivory carvings)
      - Summary of paper, The Fateful Year by W. M. Wallace
      - Paper, Defense (author unkown)
    - Schedules of metings, 1978-1979 (Folder 4)
  - 1979-1980
    - Summaries of meetings and minutes, October 1979-April 1980 (Folder 5)
      - Minutes
      - Precis of Paper
      - Summary of paper, Henry, Hudson and Beaver by John W. Paton
      - Summary of talk, Freud Never Cured An Eskimo February 4, 1980
    - Schedules of meetings, 1979-1980 (Folder 6)
    - Reply cards, 1980 (Folder 7)
  - 1980-1981
    - Summaries of meetings and minutes, 1980-1981
      - Minutes
      - Memos
      - Old Woman River by W.M.
      - 1902 Summary
      - A précis of a presentation to the club, Nuns, A Sports Day, the Virgin Kumari, and Academia, given on May 4, 1981
      - Speech, The Story of Penicillin, by Max Tishler, November 2, 1981
    - Schedules of meetings, 1980-1981
  - 1981-1982 (Folder 10)
    - Schedules of meetings
  - 1982 (Folder 11)
    - Minutes
    - Speech by Henry J. Naruk (untitled)
    - In Defense of the Hangman, February 1, 1982 (2 copies)
    - Soldiers Stones
    - Wilson at Wesleyan by Willard M. Wallace
    - Recollections of Wesleyan in the 1920s
    - Outline of Mr. Dunham's paper on Bombs Away
  - 1982-1983 (Folder 12)
    - Schedules of meetings
  - 1983 (Folder 13)
    - Minutes
    - Precis of paper, Veritas?
    - Precis of Except for Money
    - Middlesex Memorial Hospital Community Mental Health Clinic, summary of paper, YAC
  - 1983-1984 (Folder 14)
    - Schedules of meetings
  - 1984 (Folder 15)
    - Minutes
    - Was Lavius the One?
    - Abstract of talk on Joel Barlow
    - Precis, A Slight Case of McCarthyism
    - Precis, Are There Limits to Genetic Engineering?
    - Summary of paper, Expectations, Possibilities, and Realties by Gordon B. McWilliams
    - Precis, J.W.C. Pennington
  - 1984-1985 (Folder 16)
    - Schedules of meetings
  - 1985 (Folder 17)
    - Minutes
    - Speech, Lui, Mu and Jimmy, about trip to China
    - Speech, Jouney to Outer Space
    - Speech, Was Lavius the One?
  - 1985-1986 (Folder 18)
    - Precis of A Crisis of Presidential Succession in a Land of Kings, by Karl E. Scheibe
    - Speech, Learning the Hard Way: 1758, 1775, 1815
    - Precis, Una Passeggiata
  - 1986-1987 (Folder 19)
    - Minutes
    - Speech, An Eighteenth Century Loner
    - Summary of paper, The Common Bowl
    - Paper, Plauge-American Style
    - Results of anonymous questionnaire about admitting women to the Conversation Club
    - Newspaper article about Conversation Club member Rev. Joseph R. Swain Jr.
    - Pamphlet from funeral service of Rev. Joseph R. Swain Jr.
    - Precis, Hiki Ni Kidole
  - 1987-1988 (Folder 20)
    - Precis, Looking Backward
    - Summary of speech, Seven Sleepless Years
    - Market to Market, Bah Humbug
    - Precis, Fifty Million Dollars Per Year
    - P A Commemorative Pamphlet, 1862-1962-1987 (2 copies)
  - 1988-1989 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Minutes
    - Precis, The Athroposphere: What Are We Doing With It?
    - Precis, Zitti, Zitti, Piano, Piano!
    - Precis, Winslow Homer
    - Precis, An Alsatian Elegy
    - Hartford Canoe Club pamphlet
  - 1989-1990 (Folder 2)
    - Mr. Barlow's speech on Parks and Fields and the metaphysics of baseball
    - Precis, Exit Parens: Init Lex
    - Precis, Blowin' Snow paper to be delivered by Karl Scheibe
  - Membership and attendance, 1980-1989 (Folder 3)
  - 1990-1991 (Folder 4)
    - Minutes
    - Speech, R.E. Litigant
    - Speech, Q is for Quadruped
    - Speech, Count the Days
    - Precis, These Are A Few Of My Favorite Theorems
  - 1991-1992 (Folder 5)
    - Speech, When I Was A Lady
    - Speech, Why Are Our Children Having Children?
    - Speech, Diary of a Frenchman
    - Precis, The Overworked American
    - Precis of offering at Conversation Club (essay on different types of thinkers, i.e. are you a fox or a hedgehog?)
  - 1992-1993 (Folder 6)
    - La Plume de ma Tante and the Old School Tie
    - Ever Since Columbus
    - Abstract, Knute Kenneth Rocknue, a Legend in His Time
    - At the Gates, by Peter Frenzel
    - Precis, Little Johnny Riordan, a talk given by George Creeger
    - Abstract, The Couch and the Mirror
    - Middletown 2000
  - 1993-1994 (Folder 7)
    - Minutes
    - Precis, One's Name is One's Destiny
    - Speech, Fat Mary
    - Precis, The Far Shore by Derry D'Oench
    - Estado Libre Asociado-The 1993 Puerto Rican Referendum
    - Precis What's a Nice Girl Like Me Doing in an Old Boys' Club Like This?
    - Synopsis of paper Broken Heaventalk by Jon Barlow
  - 1994-1995 (Folder 8)
    - Minutes
    - Precis, Extreme Groups by Karl Scheibe
    - Summary, Economy, Unexpectedness, and Inevitability
    - Precis, The Simple Machine
    - Paper, Fair Trail-Free Press
    - Speech, A Twirl of Colors by David Lavine
    - Precis, Life After Wesleyan? by Edgar F. Beckham
  - 1995-1996 (Folder 9)
    - Minutes
    - Handwritten notes from meetings on small note pad paper
    - Speech, Lady Gregory
    - Abstract of paper on Education
    - Precis, HardDrive Memory: Around the World on a Laptop
    - Speech, Where's the Beef?
  - 1996-1997 (Folder 10)
    - Minutes
    - Abstract, The Trojan Horse in our Midst-Friend or Foe?
    - Abstract, What You See
    - Abstract, Caruso in Petticoats, about Rosa Ponselle, opera singer from Meriden, Connecticut
    - Abstract, The Good, the Bad, and the Ugly
    - Letter to the club members about Proposed nomination conventions
    - Precis, The End of the Affair
  - 1997-1998 (Folder 11)
    - Minutes
    - Abstract, Keener Sounds
    - Precis, Sagarmartha
    - Abstract, They don't make 'em like this any more
    - Abstract, Man, Reproduction, and the 20th Century
    - Abstract, CASSP
    - Abstract, The Tongues of Fire
    - Abstract, Middletown Lawyers and Other Colorful Characters, 1789-1813
    - Handwritten club meeting notes on notepad paper
  - 1998-1999 (Folder 12)
    - Minutes
    - Abstract, Dear Miss Lucy
    - Abstract, Sweet Are the Uses of Adversity: Federal Patronage of the Arts in the Great Depression, by Willian J. Barber
    - Abstract, Lost in the Parking Lot by Robert L. Kirkpatrick, Jr.
    - Abstract, Charley at the Bat by Jon Barlow
    - Abstract, Fore
    - Abstract, Inappropriate Relations and the Twentieth Century Decline of the Nation State
    - Precis, Loss by Derry D'Oench
    - Notes on the nomination process
- Addition of June 2008 (Acc. 2008-10), 1862-1987
  The materials in this series have been arranged roughly chronologically.
  - Program cards, 1870-1963 (Box 8)
    These were sent to members prior to each meeting. They list current members and the host, topic, and speaker for the upcoming meeting.
  - Club member index cards, 1862-1874 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Club Notes: a paper read at the regular meeting of the Conversational Club, 22 March 1880 (Folder 2)
  - Club member index cards, 1888-1959 (Folder 3)
  - Anniversary meeting programs, 1902, 1912, 1922 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Season programs, 1911-1914, 1916-1918, 1925-1926, 1965-1971, 1973-1974 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Group photo, circa 1948-1949 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Socratic Literary Society, 1950-1953 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Group photo with negative, circa 1960 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Meeting photos with negatives, circa 1960 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Club member index cards: present members at Centennial, 1962 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1966 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Hosts, 1965-1968, 1972-1984, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Financial information, 1963-1967 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Richard Winslow correspondence, 1975-1983 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Financial information, 1980-1981 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Administrative materials, 1983-1984 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - List of dates when constitutional votes were taken (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Paper about Mayan culture, undated (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - The Santiago Campaign: some personal experiences, by Rev. John D. Welwood, undated (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Taboo by Raymond Walsh, undated (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Town Clerk's office: notes (Box 10, Folder 19)
- Addition of December 2009 (Acc. 2009-50), 2003-2006
  - Minutes and Abstracts, January 2003-May 2006 (Box 10, Folder 20)